# Dr Rachel Cooper

BSc, Ph.D, CPsychol

Data scientist with a background in psychology. Over 9 years of experience in academic institutions conducting research, teaching statistics and managing teams. Possessing excellent analytic, communication and problem solving skills as well as passion for mission driven organisations.

## **EXPERIENCE**

## SMRS, Data Scientist

2022 - present

- Designed and implemented innovative data science solutions to optimise unbiased recruitment and improve culture for businesses and universities.
- Presented proposals, written reports, dashboards and presentations to clients.
- Projects included geospatial analysis, propensity modelling, pipeline modelling, media spend optimisation, competitor analysis and network analysis.

## S2DS Pivigo, Data Science Fellow

2022

- Used novel machine learning techniques to optimise the reach and funding of the charity National Childbirth Trust by building a data-driven pricing structure.
- Team coding in Python to provide new insights weekly.

## University of Essex, Lecturer

2017 - 2019

- Developed and coordinated undergraduate and postgraduate courses, teaching statistics, research methods and psychology.
- Supervised undergraduate and postgraduate research projects.
- Enacted the role of ambassador for disabled students.

### Newham College University Center, Lecturer

2015 - 2017

- Developed and taught undergraduate courses in statistics and psychology.
- Supervised student research projects and provided mentoring support.

## University of Essex, Lab Technician

2015

 Managed research labs, solving software and research equipment issues, MATLAB programming support.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Essex, Colchester — Ph.D

2010 - 2014

University of Essex, Colchester — MSc Modules

2007 - 2010

Research Management (78%) Quantitative Data Analysis (73%)

Anglia Ruskin University, Cambridge — BSc

2007 - 2010

1st class honours

London,

+44 7946547482

rachel.cooper01@gmail.com

github.com/Rachel-0 linkedin.com/in/rachel-coo per001/

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Advanced: Python, Matlab, SPSS, Excel.

Intermediate: Tableau, Git, web scraping, geospatial analysis.

Python libraries: Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, NLTK, BeautifulSoup, Geopandas, Selenium, Scikit Learn, Plotly, Folium.

Advanced statistics:

Supervised and unsupervised machine learning, regression, ANOVA, dimension reduction, path analysis, clustering, network analysis, segmentation.

## **SOFT SKILLS**

**Presentation**: international conferences, lectures, workshops, public events

Team leading and participation for teaching, research and data science

Mentoring of students, Mental Health First Aid (MHFAE, 2018)

### **GRANTS AWARDED**

University of Essex Scholarship for Ph.D research (£48,000)

2 x EPS Grindley grant (£1000)